{"test_questions": [[{"question": "Diamond is a paramagnetic material.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Diamond is diamagnetic."}, {"question": "Which capacitor-store higher amount of energy?", "opta": "Air capacitor", "optb": "Paper capacitor", "optc": "Mica capacitor", "optd": "Plastic film capacitor", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Energy stored is proportional to capacitance and capacitance is proportional to permittivity."}, {"question": "Above ferroelectric curie temperature, spontaneous polarization in ferroelectric materials becomes stronger.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Spontaneous polarization vanishes above ferro-electric Curie temperature."}, {"question": "In paramagnetic materials", "opta": "permanent magnetic dipoles exist but the interaction between neighbouring dipoles is negligible", "optb": "permanent magnetic dipole do not exist", "optc": "permanent magnetic dipoles exist and the interaction between neighbouring dipoles is very strong", "optd": "permanent magnetic dipole moment may or may not exist", "ans": "A", "explanation": "In paramagnetic materials interaction between neighbouring dipoles is negligible."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  Atomic number of sodium is 11.Reason (R):  Sodium has a body centred cubic lattice.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Atomic number is not dependent on lattice structure."}, {"question": "The conductivity of intrinsic semiconductor is given by", "opta": "eni(\u03bcp - \u03bcn)", "optb": "eni(\u03bcp + \u03bcn)", "optc": "ni(\u03bcp + \u03bcn)", "optd": "ni(\u03bcp\u03bcn)", "ans": "B", "explanation": "For intrinsic semiconductor, \nConductivity = (Electron charge) x (Number of charge carriers) x (Sum of mobilities of holes and electrons)."}, {"question": "The core of a coil has a length of 10 cm. The self inductance is 8 mH. If the core length is doubled, all other quantities remaining the same, the self inductance will be", "opta": "32 mH", "optb": "16 mH", "optc": "8 mH", "optd": "4 mH", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Inductance is inversely proportional to the core length."}, {"question": "The minority carrier life time and diffusion constant in a semiconducting material are 100 \u03bcs and 100 cm2/s respectively. The diffusion length of carriers is", "opta": "0.1 cm", "optb": "0.01 cm", "optc": "0.0141 cm", "optd": "1 cm", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Diffusion length = sqrt(Carrier life time x Diffusion constant) = (100 x 10-6 x 100)0.5 = 0.1 cm."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  Electronic and Ionic polarization in a polyatomic gas are independent of temperature.Reason (R):  The orientation polarization is independent of temperature.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Orientation polarization is inversely proportional to temperature."}, {"question": "Two materials having temperature coefficients of 0.004 and 0.0004 respectively are joined in series. The overall temperature coefficient is likely to be", "opta": "0.08", "optb": "0.04", "optc": "0.001", "optd": "0.0001", "ans": "C", "explanation": "The overall temperature coefficient will be less than 0.004 and more than 0.0004."}, {"question": "The number of valence electrons in pentavalent impurity is", "opta": "5", "optb": "4", "optc": "3", "optd": "1", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Pentavalent means 5 valence electrons."}, {"question": "If the diameter of a wire is doubled, its current carrying capacity becomes", "opta": "one-fourth", "optb": "half", "optc": "twice", "optd": "four times", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Current carrying capacity depends on area of cross-section."}, {"question": "The law J = \u03c3E, where J is current density, \u03c3 is electrical conductivity and E is field strength is", "opta": "Ohm's law", "optb": "Gauss law", "optc": "Ampere's law", "optd": "Biot-Savart law", "ans": "A", "explanation": "It is another form of Ohm's law."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  Silicon is less sensitive to changes in temperature than germanium.Reason (R):  Cut in voltage in silicon is less than that in germanium.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Cut in voltage of silicon is higher than that in germanium."}, {"question": "Material which lack permanent magnetic dipoles are known as", "opta": "paramagnetic", "optb": "diamagnetic", "optc": "ferromagnetic", "optd": "ferrimagnetic", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Diamagnetic materials have no permanent magnetic diploes."}, {"question": "A parallel plate capacitor has its length, width and separation doubled. It fringing effects are neglected, to keep the capacitance same, the dielectric constant must be", "opta": "halved", "optb": "kept the same", "optc": "doubled", "optd": "made 4 times", "ans": "A", "explanation": ". When dimensions are changed, A become four times and d becomes twice.\nSince \u22080 is constant, \u2208r must be halved to keep C constant."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  In imperfect capacitors, the current does not lead the applied ac voltage by 90\u00b0.Reason (R):  When subjected to ac fields, the dielectric constant can be expressed as \u2208'r - j\u2208\"r.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Imaginary part of \u2208r gives rise to absorption of energy by the material from alternating field. \nHence current does not lead the voltage by 90\u00b0."}, {"question": "In atomic physics, a state with l = 0 is called p state.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The state with l = 0 is called s state."}, {"question": "If a sample of germanium and a sample of silicon have the same impurity density and are kept at room temperature", "opta": "both will have equal value of resistivity", "optb": "both will have equal negative resistivity", "optc": "resistivity of germanium will be higher than that of silicon", "optd": "resistivity of silicon will be higher than that of germanium", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Resistivity of silicon is more than that of germanium."}, {"question": "When an electric field E is applied to solid and liquid insulating materials, the internal field Ei acting at the location of atom is such that", "opta": "Ei = E", "optb": "Ei > E", "optc": "Ei < E", "optd": "Ei may be equal to or less than E", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The actual field seen by an atom is larger than applied field."}, {"question": "Which element exhibits the property of inertia?", "opta": "Resistance", "optb": "Capacitance", "optc": "Inductance", "optd": "Both resistance and inductance", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Inductance opposes rise and decay of current. Hence it has the property of inertia."}, {"question": "For a permanent magnetic material", "opta": "the residual induction and coercive field should be large", "optb": "the residual induction and coercive field should be small", "optc": "area of hysteresis loop should be small", "optd": "initial relative permeability should be high", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Materials suitable for permanent magnet have large hysteresis loop.\nHence residual and coercive field are large."}, {"question": "In a coaxial cable, braided copper is used for", "opta": "conductor", "optb": "shield", "optc": "dielectric", "optd": "jacket", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Braided material is used for shield."}, {"question": "The hysteresis phenomenon in ferromagnetic materials exists at all temperatures.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Hysteresis phenomenon exists below ferromagnetic curie temperature."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  Magnetic susceptibility of diamagnetic materials is much less than that of paramagnetic materials.Reason (R):  For diamagnetic as well as paramagnetic materials, \u03bcr is nearly equal to 1.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Magnetic susceptibility = (\u03bcr - 1)H. \nFor diamagnetic and paramagnetic materials magnetic susceptibility is very very small and \u03bcr = 1."}, {"question": "The attraction between the nucleus and valence electron of copper atom is", "opta": "zero", "optb": "weak", "optc": "strong", "optd": "either zero or strong", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The valence electron, in copper atom, can be easily detached from nucleus."}, {"question": "If the temperature of an extrinsic semiconductor is increased so that the intrinsic carrier concentration is doubled, then", "opta": "the majority carrier density is doubled", "optb": "the minority carrier density is doubled", "optc": "the minority carrier density becomes 4 times the original value", "optd": "both the majority and minority carrier densities double", "ans": "D", "explanation": "As the intrinsic carrier concentration is doubled, the concentration of both electrons and holes is doubled."}, {"question": "There is no hysteresis phenomenon is any dielectric material.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Hysteresis phenomenon exists in dielectic materials."}, {"question": "The units of \u03bc0 and \u03bcr are", "opta": "H/m for both", "optb": "H/m for \u03bcr and no units for \u03bc0", "optc": "H/m for \u03bc0 and no units for \u03bcr", "optd": "Wb/m for \u03bc0 and no units for \u03bcr", "ans": "C", "explanation": "\u03bcr is only a numeric."}, {"question": "In metals the valence electron wave functions are strongly perturbed by the presence of neighbouring atoms.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "In a metal valence electrons are shared by all atoms."}, {"question": "For a paramagnetic material, susceptiblity increases with increasing temperature.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Susceptibility \u221d ."}, {"question": "Hydrogen is used in", "opta": "large size transformers", "optb": "MCB", "optc": "large size generators", "optd": "circuit breakers", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Modem large size generators have hydrogen cooling."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  Ferroelectric materials have spontaneous polarization.Reason (R):  Above curie temperature, \u2208 =  for ferro-electric materials.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Both A and R are correct. Spontaneous polarization vanishes above ferroelectric curie temperature."}, {"question": "If e is the charge of an electron, R is the radius of its orbit and \u03c9 is the angular velocity of electron, the magnetic dipole moment \u03bcm of the orbit is |\u03bcm| = e\u03c9R2.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "1 \u03bcm 1 = 0.5 e\u03c9r2."}, {"question": "If \u2208r' and \u2208r\" are the real and imaginary parts of complex dielectric constant \u2208r, and \u03b4 is the loss angle. Then", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "tan \u03b4 = \u2208'\u2208\"", "optd": "tan \u03b4 = 1 - \u2208'", "ans": "B", "explanation": "If \u2208r\" = 0, \u03b4 = 0."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  At a temperature of 1000 K, thermionic emission current is about 0.1 A/cm2 of surface.Reason (R):  Thermionic emission current is given by Ith = SA0 T2 e-Ew/kT.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "A", "explanation": "If different values are substituted in the equation for Ith the value of emission current comes out to be about 0.1 A/cm2."}, {"question": "At room temperature, the current in intrinsic semiconductor is due to", "opta": "holes", "optb": "electrons", "optc": "ions", "optd": "holes and electrons", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Both electrons and holes contribute to flow of current in semiconductors."}, {"question": "Ferroelectric materials are those which", "opta": "cannot be polarized", "optb": "have a permanent polarization", "optc": "have ae equal to zero", "optd": "have \u03bcp = 0", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Ferroelectric materials have permanent polarization."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  Power loss in a conductor of resistance P = I2R.Reason (R):  When a conductor is carrying current with current density J as a result of applied field E, then heat developed/m3/ second = JE.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Heat developed depends an power loss."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  For Diamond, \u03bcr = 1Reason (R):  Diamond is a diamagnetic material.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "A", "explanation": "For diamagnetic materials \u03bcr = 1."}, {"question": "If n denotes principal quantum number, the angular quantum number l = 0, 1... (n - 1).", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Angular quantum number determines the angular momentum of electron."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  In a perfect capacitor, the current density is given by \u03c9 \u22080E0\u2208'rcos(\u03c9t + 90\u00b0), where \u2208r' is real part of dielectric constant.Reason (R):  In a perfect capacitor, dielectric losses are zero.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "A", "explanation": "If dielectric losses are zero, the current in capacitor leads the applied voltage by 90\u00b0. \nAlso imaginary part of is \u2208r is zero."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  For a solenoid having N turns, .Reason (R):  For all magnetic materials, B increases linearly with I.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Increase of B with I is not linear. Hence R is false."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  From the slope of the line in Figure, we can find permanent dipole moment of the molecules.Reason (R):  Total polarization of a polyatomic gas is given by P = N(ae + ai + \u03bc2p / 3kT)E.", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The slope of the line in figure is . \nSince the total polarization is as given by the expression, we can find the permanent dipole moment of the molecules from the slope."}, {"question": "Assertion (A):  If E is available energy state eV and EF is Fermi level, then probability of energy state E being occupied = 0.5.Reason (R): .", "opta": "Both A and R are true and R is correct explanation of A", "optb": "Both A and R are true but R is not correct explanation of A", "optc": "A is true but R is false", "optd": "A is false but R is true", "ans": "B", "explanation": "E = EF, f(E) = 0.5."}, {"question": "If a piece of wood is placed in a magnetic field", "opta": "the magnetic field will not be affected", "optb": "the magnetic lines of force will bend towards the piece", "optc": "the magnetic lines of force will bend away from the piece", "optd": "the flux may increase or decrease", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Wood is non-magnetic."}, {"question": "The apparent capacitance at a high angular frequency \u03c9 of an air cored capacitor having capacitance C and inductance L is given by", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The combination can be represented as L and C in series.\n.\nTherefore, ."}, {"question": "The number of valence electrons in donor impurity are", "opta": "5", "optb": "4", "optc": "3", "optd": "1", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Donor impurity has 5 valence electrons (while silicon has 4 valence electrons).\nHence donor impurity can donate electrons."}, {"question": "In a true valence crystal, the bonding between the atoms is accomplished by the sharing of valence electrons.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Sharing of valence electons is a characteristic of true valence crystal."}, {"question": "Which of the following are donor impurities? GoldPhosphorusBoronAntimonyArsenicInduim Select the correct answer using the following codes", "opta": "1, 2, 3", "optb": "1, 2, 4, 6", "optc": "3, 4, 5, 6", "optd": "2, 4, 5", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Donor impurities have five valence electrons."}]]}